Guide to the Donald Grant Mitchell Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Donald Grant Mitchell papers
1787-1936
YCAL MSS 492
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.26
(15 boxes)
The Donald Grant Mitchell papers contain original correspondence and manuscripts by the prominent nineteenth-century New Haven-area author. Correspondents include Henry Ward Beecher, Henry Augustin Beers, George Washington Cable, William Maxwell Evarts, Fitz-Greene Halleck, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Thomas Raynesford Lounsbury, Hamilton Wright Mabie, Noah Porter, Theodore Roosevelt, Charles Scribner, Edmund Clarence Stedman, Harriet Beecher Stowe, and others. Writings include drafts for published and unpublished work and journals, including substantive drafts for Fresh Gleanings (1847), American Lands and Letters (1897-1899), English Lands, Letters and Kings (1889-1890), and Wet Days at Edgewood (1865), as well as an unpublished "History of Venice." Other materials include biographical and bibliographical material, financial and legal records, photographs, and printed ephemera.
Mitchell, Donald Grant, 1822-1908
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired through various gifts and purchases from 1938 to 1974. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Scrapbooks classed as Za M692 +S1.
Donald Grant Mitchell Papers (MSS #140). New Haven Museum, New Haven, Connecticut.
Donald Grant Mitchell (1822-1908)
Donald Grant Mitchell, essayist and novelist, was born in Norwich, Connecticut, graduated from Yale College in 1841 and, after serving abroad briefly as U.S. consul in Venice, Italy, from 1853 to 1854, settled near New Haven, Connecticut. Mitchell wrote literary criticism, travel literature, and volumes of essays on rural themes, including Reveries of a Bachelor (1850), My Farm of Edgewood: A Country Book (1863), and Rural Studies (1867). Other works include the novel Doctor Johns (1866), About Old Story Tellers (1878), and American Lands and Letters (1897–1899).
Scope and Contents
The Donald Grant Mitchell papers contain original correspondence and manuscripts by the prominent nineteenth-century New Haven area author. Correspondents include Henry Ward Beecher, Henry Augustin Beers, George Washington Cable, William Maxwell Evarts, Fitz-Greene Halleck, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Thomas Raynesford Lounsbury, Hamilton Wright Mabie, Noah Porter, Theodore Roosevelt, Charles Scribner, Edmund Clarence Stedman, Harriet Beecher Stowe, and others. Writings include drafts for published and unpublished work and journals, including substantive drafts for Fresh Gleanings (1847), American Lands and Letters (1897-1899), English Lands, Letters and Kings (1889-1890), and Wet Days at Edgewood (1865), as well as an unpublished "History of Venice." Other materials include biographical and bibliographical material, financial and legal records, photographs, and printed ephemera.
Arrangement
Arranged according to Za Mitchell numbers in card catalog.
American literature -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Authors -- United States -- 19th century; Beecher, Henry Ward, 1813-1887; Beers, Henry A. (Henry Augustin), 1847-1926; Cable, George Washington, 1844-1925; Evarts, William Maxwell, 1818-1901; Halleck, Fitz-Greene, 1790-1867; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894; Lounsbury, Thomas R., 1838-1915; Mabie, Hamilton Wright, 1846-1916; Mitchell, Donald Grant, 1822-1908; Porter, Noah, 1811-1892; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Scribner, Charles, 1821-1871; Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1833-1908; Stowe, Harriet Beecher, 1811-1896
- Correspondence
  - Mitchell, Donald Grant, [circa 1840-1905]; 9 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Contains letters from Mitchell to others, including William Williams, Charles Scribner, and Mary (Perkins) Goddard
  - Beers, Henry Augustin, 1886 June 3 (Box 1)
  - Cable, George Washington, 1904 March 1 (Box 1)
  - Curwen, John, 1889-1900, undated (Box 1)
  - Evarts, William Maxwell, 1878 April (Box 1)
  - Gilman, Daniel Coit, 1883, 1891 (Box 1)
  - Harper & Brothers, publishers, 1847-1857 (Box 1)
  - Hubbard, Gardiner Greene, 1897 July 28 (Box 1)
  - Huntington, William Henry, [circa 1858-1884] (Box 1)
  - Law, S. D., 1880 January 17 (Box 1)
  - Lounsbury, Thomas Raynesford, 1889-1899 (Box 1)
  - Mabie, Hamilton Wright, 1883, 1889 (Box 1)
  - Marble Annie (Russell), 1906 (Box 1)
  - Mathews, Cornelius, 1853 April 20 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, [circa 1851-1890] (Box 2)
  - Munger, Theodore Thornton, 1903 March 4 (Box 2)
  - Olcott, James B., 1891 (Box 2)
  - Peck, Tracy, 1901 November 2 (Box 2)
  - Porter, Noah, 1884 (Box 2)
  - Pusey, Cécile (Guyot), 1849 May 17 (Box 2)
  - Rantoul, Robert Samuel, 1904 August 23 (Box 2)
  - Scribner, Arthur Hawley, 1889, 1892 (Box 2)
  - Scribner, Charles (1821-1871), 1856-1866 (Box 2)
  - Scribner, Charles (1854-1930), 1883-1907 (Box 2)
  - Smyth, Albert Henry, 1889-1899 (Box 2)
  - Stokes, Olivia Egleston Phelps, 1901 October 24 (Box 2)
  - Weir, John Ferguson, 1894 May 15 (Box 2)
  - Welles, Edwin Stanley, 1894 February 6 (Box 2)
  - Yarnall, Thomas Coffin, 1901, 1905 (Box 2)
- Third party correspondence
  - Bigelow, John, 1906 November 8 (Box 2)
  - Blake, Henry Taylor, 1886 May 17 (Box 2)
  - Hutchinson, Thomas, 1896, 1902 (Box 2)
  - Kennedy, John Pendleton, 1853 June 15 (Box 2)
  - Mitchell, Lucretia Mumford (Woodbridge), 1809-1832 (Box 2)
  - Mitchell, Mary Frances (Pringle), 1862-1884 (Box 2)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, 1907 (Box 2)
  - Charles Scribner & Sons, 1872-1906; 2 (Box 2)
    Includes memoranda of agreement
  - Shaw, Thomas, 1795 March 10 (Box 2)
- Writings and Related Papers
  - Bibliography of his own work, 1909, undated (Box 2)
    Includes letters to Walter L. Mitchell
  - Bibliographies of other works, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Bride of the Ice-King", [1864] (Box 2)
  - Old Christmas Reminiscences, undated (Box 2)
  - Dedication for American Lands and Letters, 1897 February 22 (Box 2)
  - Fresh Gleanings, 1847 July (Box 2)
  - American Lands and Letters, undated (Box 3)
  - English Lands, Letters and Kings, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous manuscript fragments, undated (Box 3)
  - Lectures and speeches, undated (Box 3)
  - Farmers' Homes, undated (Box 3)
  - [Art and common sense], undated (Box 4)
  - "Towns: Streets", undated (Box 4)
  - "Parks: etc.", undated (Box 4)
  - "Buildings", undated (Box 4)
  - Essay fragments, undated (Box 4)
  - Typescript copy of inscription, undated (Box 4)
  - Private papers, 1908, undated (Box 4)
  - Journals, 1859, undated; 5 (Box 4)
  - Journal of finances and writings, undated (Box 5)
  - Essay on farms and farm houses, undated (Box 5)
  - Royalty statements from Charles Scribner & Sons, 1850-1936 (Box 5)
  - Wet Days at Edgewood, undated (Box 5)
  - Journal, Index of agriculture, 1837 (Box 6)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - Typescripts of selected correspondence, undated (Box 6)
    - Beecher, Henry Ward; Beecher, Catherine E., 1869, 1873 (Box 6)
    - Beers, Henry Augustin, 1886 July 8 (Box 6)
    - Cable, George Washington, 1899 (Box 6)
    - Cooke, John Esten, 1899 (Box 6)
    - Curtis, George William, 1859, 1885 (Box 6)
    - Fields, James T., 1863-1866 (Box 6)
    - Halleck, Fitz-Greene, 1869 (Box 6)
    - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1869-1891 (Box 6)
    - Larcom, Lucy, 1869-1870 (Box 6)
    - Mabie, Hamilton Wright, 1902, undated (Box 6)
    - Porter, Noah, 1865 May (Box 6)
    - Sigourney, Lydia, 1863 (Box 6)
    - Simms, William Gilmore, 1853, undated (Box 6)
    - Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1866-1897 (Box 6)
    - Stowe, Harriet Beecher, 1868-1870 (Box 6)
    - Taylor, Bayard, 1862-1869 (Box 6)
    - White, Richard Grant, 1850, 1883 (Box 6)
    - Winter, William, 1896-1908 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1851-1906, undated; 2 (Box 6)
    - Catalog of autograph letters, [circa 1900] (Box 6)
  - Outgoing
    - Mitchell, Donald Grant, 1848-1904, undated; 12 (Box 6)
- Writings and Other Papers
  - Biographical sketch of Louis Mitchell, undated (Box 6)
  - "A History of Venice", 1857, undated; 16 (Box 7)
  - History of Venice: lecture, undated (Box 7)
  - Journal, History of Venice, undated (Box 8)
  - Journal: Venetian notes, undated (Box 8)
  - Journal: History of Venice, undated (Box 8)
  - Notes on Venetian history by Louis Mitchell, undated (Box 8)
  - Notes on Italy especially relating to Venice, undated (Box 8)
  - Appendix of the statutes of the Inquisition, undated (Box 8)
  - Catalogo dei libri della Biblioteca d' Brera, undated (Box 8)
  - Valery's Travels in Italy, undated (Box 8)
  - Lectures II-VI, undated (Box 8)
  - Commonplace book, undated (Box 9)
- Unsorted Material
  - Letters and clippings sent between William Winter and Mitchell, undated (Box 9)
  - Fan mail sent to Mitchell, 1844-1900, undated (Box 9)
  - "Lorgnette material", 1850-1851 (Box 9)
  - De Koven, Henry letter, undated (Box 9)
  - Dunn, Waldo H. letter, 1902 April 12 (Box 9)
    Poem: On the 80th birthday of Donald Grant Mitchell
  - Fragment of address from Oliver Wendell Holmes to Mitchell, undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 9)
  - Letters sent between Waldo H. Dunn and Mitchell, 1902-1906 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1897-1903 (Box 9)
  - Photographs, interiors of Edgewood, with notes by Waldo H. Dunn, undated (Box 9)
  - Summons signed by Stephen Mix Mitchell, grandfather of Donald Grant Mitchell, 1787 December (Box 9)
  - Printed matter by and about Mitchell, 1856-1901, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - Proof for preface to Doctor Johns, undated (Box 9)
  - Holograph preface to the Edgewood edition of Works of Donald Grant Mitchell, undated (Box 9)
  - Holograph of Chapter VII of the first volume of American Lands and Letters, undated (Box 9)
  - Scrapbooks, 1848, undated (Box 10)
    Originally the day book of attorney Levi H. Goddard, including financial records and clippings of Mitchell's Letters from Paris (1848) and Capitol Sketches
    Also stored at Za M692 +S1
  - The Dignity of Learning: A Valedictory Oration, 1841 (Box 10)
  - Typescript of Letters from Paris, undated (Box 10)
  - Card catalog of Mitchell's library, undated (Box 11)
  - "J. G. Dill's Best Cut Plug" tobacco tin, 1843, undated (Box 12)
    Contains Mitchell's Skull and Bones pin, undated, and an award medal granted to Mitchell by the New York State Agriculture Society, 1843.
  - Photographs and engravings of Donald Grant Mitchell, 1903, 1905, undated; 6 folders (Box 13)
  - Scrapbook of engravings, undated (Box 14)
  - Awards, 1878, 1879, 1883; 3 folders (Box 15 (Oversize))